# Nikola Sander

# CURRICULUM VITAE

★ +43 1 31336 7738

implies nikola@nikolasander.com
implies www.nikolasander.com
implies nikolasander



I'm a human/population geographer interested in internal & international migration, urbanisation, population projections and data visualisation.

I'm excited to announce that I will join the Population Research Centre at the University of Groningen as Assistant Professor of Population Geography in March 2016.

	Education
Apr 2006 - Feb 2011	<b>PhD in Geography</b> , <i>University of Queensland, Australia</i> , Title: "Retirement Migration of the Baby Boomers in Australia: Beach, Bush or Busted?", <i>Advisor: Professor Martin Bell</i> .
Oct 2007 - Mar 2008	International Max Planck Research School for Demography, Max Planck Institute for Demographic Research, Germany.
Jun 2007 - Aug 2007	<b>Young Scientists Summer Program</b> , World Population Program, International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis, Austria.
Oct 1999 - Jul 2005	<b>Diplom in Geography (Master's equivalent)</b> , Eberhard-Karls University Tübingen, Germany.
Apr 2004 - Nov 2004	Research stay, Griffith University, Gold Coast, Australia.
Feb 2003 - July 2003	Study abroad, Flinders University, Adelaide, Australia.
1998	Abitur (baccalaureate), Konrad-Heresbach Gymnasium Mettmann, Germany.

### Current Positions

Since Nov 2010	Research Scholar,	vienna institute oi	i Demograpny,	Austrian Academy	/ 01 SCI-
	ences, Austria.				

since Jan 2011 **Research Team Leader 'Migration & Education'**, Wittgenstein Centre for Demography and Global Human Capital, Austria.

## Previous Positions

Aug 2010	- Oct 2010	Associate Research Scholar, World Population Program, International Insti-
		tute for Applied Systems Analysis, Austria.
Mar. 0000	May 0007	Because Assistant Cabasi of Congression Blancing and Environmental Man

May 2006 – Mar 2007	Research Assistant, School of Geography, Planning and Environmental Man-
	agement, The University of Queensland, Australia, working for the Queensland
	Centre for Population Research.

Jun 2004 – Feb 2005 **Research Assistant**, School of Environmental and Applied Sciences, Griffith University, Australia, conducting case studies on amenity migration in inland Australia.

## Teaching Experience

- 2011 **Guest lecturer**, *Department of Tourism and Hospitality Management, MODUL University Vienna*, Course: Latest Trends and Innovations in Tourism.
- 2008 **Guest lecturer**, School of Geography, Planning and Environmental Management, The University of Queensland, Australia, Course: Applied Demography.
- 2006 2008 **Teaching Assistant**, School of Geography, Planning and Environmental Management, The University of Queensland, Australia.

## Selected Scholarships and Awards

- 2010 RHD Editorial Support Award for PhD thesis editing, *University of Queensland, Australia (AU\$1,000)*.
- 2006 2010 **UQ Research Higher Degree Conference Travel Award**, *University of Queensland*, *Australia (AU\$7,000)*.
- 2006 2010 **UQ International Scholarship (UQI)**, University of Queensland, Australia (AU\$103,400).
  - 2006 International Postgraduate Research Scholarship (IPRS), University of New South Wales, Australia (declined).
  - 2003 Baden-Württemberg Exchange Program Award, Flinders University, Australia.

## Supervision of Graduate Students

- 2014 Jonas Vogt, Masters Student, Vienna Institute of Demography.
- 2011 Yang Li, YSSP Student, International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis.
- 2011 Gernot Pucher, Masters Student, Vienna Institute of Demography.

# Funding Support

### 2010 - 2014 European Research Council Advanced Grant,

PI: Prof. Wolfgang Lutz.

Title: "Forecasting Societies' Adaptive Capacities to Climate Change".

### 2007 - 2010 European Commission,

WP leader: Prof. Vegard Skirbeck,

Title: "Peri-urban Land Use Relationships: Strategies & Sustainability Assessment Tools for Urban-Rural Linkages" (PLUREL).

## 2006 - 2010 Australian Research Council Discovery Grant,

PI: Prof. Martin Bell,

Title: "Understanding the Structure of Internal Migration in Australia".

# Participation in Externally Funded Projects

# 2014 - 2015 Coordinated the Austrian Case Study on student mobility for the ESRC Centre for Population Change,

PI: Prof Allan Findlay, University of St Andrews,

Project title: CPC-II - Mobility Strand - WP 3.2 "Dynamics and policy implications of changes in student mobility".

### 2009 - 2010 Authored a report on retirement migration in urban Europe.

PI: Prof Vegard Skirbekk, IIASA,

Project title: "Peri-urban Land Use Relationships - Strategies and Sustainability Assessment Tools for Urban-Rural Linkages" (PLUREL).

### Selected International Collaborators

Prof Phil Rees, University of Leeds, UK, on modelling migration in population projections.

Prof John Stillwell, University of Leeds, UK, on modelling and visualising interregional migration.

Prof Martin Bell, University of Queensland, Australia, on the ARC Project "Internal Migration Around the Globe (IMAGE)".

Dr Elin Charles-Edwards, University of Queensland, Australia, on linking different types of human mobility.

Dr Thomas Esch & Dr Hannes Taubenböck, German Space Agency, Germany, on quantifying global urban growth from space.

**Prof Allan Findlay**, University of St Andrews, UK, on international student migration.

Dr Nik Lomax, University of Leeds, UK, on visualising migration flows.

## **Professional Services**

- since 2015 Population, Space & Place (Wiley), Member of the International Advisory Board.
- since 2014 Austrian Integration Fund, Member of the Jury for the Dissertation Price.
- since 2013 International Geographical Union, Commission on Population Geography, Member of the Steering Committee and Secretary.
  - 2002 University of Tübingen, Member of the Professorship Search Committee.

## Refereeing

Journals International Migration Review,

Population, Space & Place, European Journal of Population,

Demographic Research,

Journal of Population Research,

PLOS One.

Population and Environment, Comparative Population Studies,

Urban Geography.

Granting Bodies Polish National Science Centre.

# Membership of Scientific Societies

International Union for the Scientific Study of Population.

International Geographical Union.

Population Association of America.

European Association for Population Studies. Asian Population Association.

### Data Visualisations

Mar 2014 **The Global Flow of People**, *An interactive data visualisation of global migration flows, 1990-2010*, visits since March 2014: 650,000, WWW.GLOBAL-MIGRATION.INFO.

June 2014 Internal Migration in Germany, An interactive data visualisation of interregional migration flows in Germany, 1995-2010, visits since June 2014: 29,000, www.german-migration.info.

Mar 2014 Global Migration Data Sheet 2005-10, A two-sided poster for science dissemination and education. Total circulation: 5,000 copies, PDF.

## Selected Media Coverage

Der Standard Aus globaler Sicht hat Migration nicht zugenommen, by A. Pumhösel, LINK.

FAZ Land, Stadt, Glück, by L. Nienhaus, LINK.

Die Welt Junge Menschen ziehen massenhaft in die Metropolen, by D. Siems, LINK.

The Washington Post How statisticians uncovered the world's missing migrants, by A. Swanson,

LINK.

National Public Radio How Cultures Move Across Continents, by K. Manke, LINK.

New Scientist Rising tide of migration is a myth, say global stats, by J. White, LINK.

Scientific American Global Migrant Flows: An Interactive Map, by G. Giller, LINK.

Quartz/The Atlantic Where everyone in the world is migrating — in one gorgeous chart, by N.

Stockton, LINK.

FastCoExist Visualizing Which Countries People Are Trying To Get Away From, And

Where They're Going, by J. Leber, LINK.

Slate World on the Move, by J. Keating, LINK.

Telegraph Innovative graphic shows human flow across world's borders, by E.

Roberts, LINK.

Wired Addio Italia: la mecca della cultura contemporanea è la California, by G.

De Martino, LINK.

Rue89 Voici la visualisation qui cassera vos idées reçues sur l'immigration, by C.

Beal, LINK.

Der Spiegel Die Welt ist konstant in Bewegung, LINK.

ORF Globale Migration seit 1990 stabil, LINK.

Der Standard Neue Studie: Globale Migration seit 1990 nahezu unverändert, LINK.

#### Technical Skills

Graphics Adobe Illustrator & InDesign, HTML5 & CSS

Statistics Stata, R [basics]

GIS ArcGIS, QGIS

Text Markdown, LAT<sub>E</sub>X

- in press **N. Sander**. Die Zuwanderung aus Südeuropa nach Deutschland im globalen Kontext, *Berichte. Geographie und Landeskunde*.
- in press **N. Sander** & E. Charles-Edwards. Internal and International Migration, *In: Africa's Population: Demographic Dividend or Social Time Bomb?*, eds. J. May & H. Groth, Springer.
  - 2015 E. Charles-Edwards, T. Wilson & N. Sander. Visualising Australian internal and international migration flows, *Regional Studies, Regional Science*, vol. 2 (1): 431-433, PDF, LINK.
  - 2015 **N. Sander** & M. Bell. Age, Period and Cohort Effects on Migration of the Baby Boomers in Australia, *Population, Space & Place*, pre-published online 21 May 2015, **PDF**, LINK.
  - 2015 **N. Sander**. Font and Mendez (eds.): Surveying Ethnic Minorities and Immigrant Population, *European Journal of Population*, vol. 31(1): 107-108, LINK.
  - 2015 J. Stillwell, N. Lomax & N. Sander. Monitoring and Visualising Sub-national Migration Trends in the United Kingdom, *In: Planning Support Systems and Smart Cities*, pp. 427-445, eds. S. Geertman, J. Ferreira, R. Goodspeed & J. Stillwell, Springer, LINK.
  - 2015 Roland, M., P. Wiesinger & **N. Sander**. H ANHANG, *In: Malstil und Schreibsprache*, pp. 119-140, M. Roland, M. & P. Wiesinger, Austrian Academy of Sciences.
  - 2015 N. Sander & R. Bauer. Visualizing The Global Migration System, New World, vol. 2, United Nations Association of Great Britain and Northern Ireland (UNA-UK), LINK.
  - 2015 **N. Sander**. Die Welt auf Wanderschaft, *Demografische Forschung Aus Erster Hand*, Max-Planck-Institute for Demographic Research, **PDF**, LINK.
  - 2015 **N. Sander**, G. Abel & R. Bauer. Visualizing Global Migration, *Journal of International Affairs*, vol. 68(2): 272-273, Columbia University, LINK.
  - 2014 G. Abel & **N. Sander** [alphabetical order]. Quantifying Global International Migration Flows, *Science*, vol. 343 (6178): 1520-1522, **PDF**, LINK.
  - 2014 **N. Sander**. Internal migration in Germany, 1995-2010: new insights into East-West migration and re-urbanization, *Comparative Population Studies*, vol. 39(2): 217-246, **PDF**, LINK.
  - 2014 **N. Sander** & M. Bell. Migration and Retirement in the Life Course: An event history approach, *Journal of Population Research*, vol. 31(1): 1-27, **PDF**, LINK.
  - **N. Sander**, G. Abel & F. Riosmena. The Future of International Migration, *In: World Population and Human Capital in the 21st Century*, pp. 333-397, eds. W. Lutz, W. Butz & S. KC, Oxford University Press, LINK.
  - **N. Sander**. The Geography of Contemporary World Migration, *Geography Review by Hodder Education*, vol. 28(2): 20-21, LINK.
  - 2014 **N. Sander**. Deutschland in Bewegung? Neue Daten und Erkenntnisse zur globalen Migration und zur deutschen Binnenwanderung, *Bevökerungsforschung Aktuell*, vol. 35(3): 8-12, **PDF**.
  - 2014 M. Fischetti, **N. Sander** [Illustration]. The Not So Wretched Masses, *Scientific American*, vol. 310: 86, LINK.
  - 2014 **N. Sander**, G. Abel, R. Bauer & J. Schmidt. Visualising Migration Flow Data with Circular Plots, *VID Working Paper*, 2/2014, **PDF**.

- 2013 N. Sander, G. Abel & F. Riosmena. The Future of International Migration: Developing Expert-Based Assumptions for Global Population Projections, VID Working Paper, 07/2013, PDF.
- 2011 **N. Sander**, Retirement Migration of the Baby Boomers in Australia: Beach, Bush or Busted?, Ph.D. Thesis, FIGSHARE.
- 2011 **N. Sander**, V. Skirbekk, S. K.C. & E. Lundevaller. Prospects for later-life migration in urban Europe, *Project report; Peri-Urban Land Use Relationships Strategies and Sustainability Assessment Tools for Urban-Rural Linkages (PLUREL*).
- 2006 R. Buckley, **N. Sander**, C. Ollenburg & J. Warnken. Green Change: Inland Amenity Migration in Australia, *In: The Amenity Migrants: Seeking And Sustaining Mountains And Their Cultures*, pp. 278-294, ed. L. Moss, CABI, LINK.

#### Invited talks

- Sep 2015 **N. Sander**, *Myths and facts on migration in Europe and the global context [Plenary]*, Conference of the European Institute of Social Security, Vienna, Austria, Link.
- Jun 2015 **N. Sander**, *Migration in the Modern World [Opening Plenary]*, International Conference on Population Geographies, Brisbane, Australia, LINK.
- May 2015 **N. Sander**, *Quantifizierung und Visualisierung Globaler Migrationsströme*, World Demographic and Ageing Forum, St. Gallen, Switzerland, LINK.
- Oct 2014 **N. Sander**, Participant and presenter at the Workshop on Demography and Energy, organised by the King Abdullah Petroleum Studies and Research Centre (KAPSARC), Washington D.C., USA.
- Sep 2014 **N. Sander**, *Wie viele Menschen trägt die Erde?*, Helmholtz Association, Magdeburg, Germany, SLIDES.
- Aug 2014 **N. Sander**, Perception of Migration How to Change the Narratives about Migrants, UNAOC Global Forum, Bali, Indonesia, LINK.
- Apr 2014 G. Abel & **N. Sander**, *Participant and presenter at the seminar on the role of migration in population modeling*, United Nations, New York, USA, LINK.
- Jan 2014 **N. Sander** & G. Abel, *Quantifying and visualising global international migration flows in 1990-2010*, Hungarian National Statistical Office, Budapest, Hungary.
- Sep 2013 **N. Sander**, The socio-demographic characteristics of the New Highlanders and the impact of their migration behaviour on population structures in destination regions, AlpWeek, Poschiavo, Switzerland.
- May 2013 **N. Sander**, *Participant in the Workshop on Migration, Urbanization and Climate Change*, National Center for Atmospheric Research, Boulder, USA.
- Dec 2011 **N. Sander**, Participant in the Workshop on Scientific Analysis of Migration and Global Environmental Change, European Commission, Brussels, Belgium.

### Conference Presentations

- Jul 2015 **N. Sander**, R. Bauer & T. Frank, *Adding Design to the Research Process: Visualising Complex Migration Flow Data*, APA Biannual Meeting, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia, **SLIDES**.
- Jun 2015 N. Sander & R. Bauer, Internal migration in Austria along the rural-urban continuum and across the life course, 1996–2014, International Conference on Population Geographies, Brisbane, Australia, SLIDES.

- Jun 2015 **N. Sander** & R. Bauer, *How Data Visualisation Enhances the Impact and Visibility of Science*, International Conference on Population Geographies, Brisbane, Australia, **SLIDES**.
- Apr 2015 **N. Sander** & R. Bauer, *How Data Visualisation Enhances the Impact and Visibility of Science*, PAA Annual Meeting, San Diego, USA, **SLIDES**.
- Mar 2015 **N. Sander**, *Quantifizierung, Visualisierung und Kommunikation von globalen Wanderungsströmen*, DGD Jahrestagung, Berlin, Germany, **SLIDES**.
- Dec 2014 E. Charles-Edwards, T. Wilson & **N. Sander**, *Visualising Australian internal and international migration flows*, Meeting of the Australian Population Association, Hobart, Australia, **Poster**.
- Dec 2014 M. Bell, E. Charles-Edwards, P. Ueffing, A. Bernard, F. Rowe, T. Wilson, J. Cooper & **N. Sander**, *Inter-regional migration in Australia: Thirty years of change*, Meeting of the Australian Population Association, Hobart, Australia.
- Aug 2014 **N. Sander** & G. Abel, *Quantifying and visualising migration flows around the globe*, International Geographical Union, Cracow, Poland, **SLIDES**.
- Aug 2014 **N. Sander** & R. Bauer, *Data visualisation at the nexus of science and the public*, The Graphical Web, Winchester, UK, SLIDES, VIDEO.
- Jul 2014 **N. Sander**, G. Abel, R. Bauer & J. Schmidt, *Visualizing Migration Flow Data*, Migration & Development Conference, Oxford, UK, SLIDES.
- Jun 2014 **N. Sander**, P. Rees & G. Abel, *The patterns and trends in global international migration flows since 1990: a revisit with new data and methods*, European Population Conference, Budapest, Hungary, **SLIDES**.
- Jun 2014 **N. Sander**, R. Bauer & G. Abel, *Visualizing global international migration flows*, European Population Conference, Budapest, Hungary, **Poster**.
- Jun 2014 G. Abel, S. KC & **N. Sander**, Examining the role of international migration in global population projections [poster], European Population Conference, Budapest, Hungary.
- May 2014 G. Abel, S. KC & **N. Sander**, Examining the Role of International Migration in Global Population Projections, PAA Annual Meeting, Boston, USA.
- Oct 2013 **N. Sander**, G. Abel & S. KC, *The impact of alternative assumptions about migration differentials by education on projections of human capital*, Eurostat/UNECE Work Session on Demographic Projections, Rome, Italy.
- Oct 2013 **N. Sander**, Internationale Migration von und nach Deutschland: Die neue "Einwanderungswelle" aus Südeuropa in Globaler Perspektive, Deutscher Geographentag, Passau, Germany, **SLIDES**.
- Sep 2013 **N. Sander** & R. Bauer, *Binnenwanderungsmuster in Deutschland seit 1995: Allgemeine Trends und Geschlechterdifferenzen*, D-A-CH Tagung, Salzburg, Austria, **SLIDES**.
- Aug 2013 **N. Sander**, Internal Migration in Germany between reunification and financial crisis: Changes in spatial patterns and sex ratios, IUSSP Population Conference, Busan, Korea.
- Aug 2013 **N. Sander**, G. Abel & S. KC, *Innovations in International Migration for use in Global Population Projections*, IUSSP Population Conference, Busan, Korea, SLIDES.
- Jun 2013 **N. Sander**, *Transitions in Gender Ratios among Internal Migrants in Germany, 2000-2010*, Population Geography Conference, Groningen, The Netherlands.

- Jun 2013 **N. Sander**, G. Abel & S. KC, *Innovations in International Migration for use in Global Population Projections*, Population Geography Conference, Groningen, The Netherlands.
- Apr 2013 **N. Sander**, "Go West, Young Man"!? Internal Migration in Germany between Reunification and Economic Crisis [poster], PAA Annual Meeting, New Orleans, USA.
- Apr 2013 **N. Sander**, G. Abel & S. KC, *Innovations in International Migration for Use in Global Population Projections*, PAA Annual Meeting, New Orleans, USA.
- Aug 2012 **N. Sander**, *Go West, Young Man!? The spatial structure of inter-regional migration in Germany*, International Geographical Union, Cologne, Germany.
- Aug 2012 **N. Sander** & M. Bell, *Retirement Migration of the Baby Boomers in Australia:* Beach, Bush or Busted?, International Geographical Union, Cologne, Germany.
- Jun 2012 **N. Sander**, *Dynamics in the spatial structure of international migration flows between 195 countries, 1960-2010 [poster]*, European Population Conference, Stockholm, Sweden.
- Apr 2012 **N. Sander** & J. Vobecka, *A Cross-National Comparison of the Spatial Structure of Internal Migration by Level of Educational Attainment*, PAA Annual Meeting, San Francisco, USA.
- Jun 2011 **N. Sander** & M. Bell, *Retirement Migration of the Baby Boomers in Australia: Beach, Bush or Busted?*, International Conference on Population Geographies, Umea, Sweden, **SLIDES**.
- Oct 2010 **N. Sander** & V. Skirbekk, *Prospects for later-life migration in urban Europe*, International Conference on Managing the Urban-Rural Interface, Copenhagen, Denmark, **SLIDES**.
- Sep 2009 **N. Sander** & M. Bell, *Retirement migration among the baby boomers: cohort dynamics and spatial structure in Australia*, IUSSP Population Conference, Marrakesh, Morocco.
- Aug 2009 **N. Sander** & M. Bell, *Migration and Retirement in the Life Course: An event history approach*, International Conference on Population Geographies, Dartmouth, USA.

Last updated: 11 December 2015